ISABEL YOUNGS

izzyoungs@gmail.com | izzy-youngs.com | (775) 420-1217 | Washington, DC

SUMMARY:

Izzy is currently a Research Specialist at the Georgetown Massive Data Institute, where she collaborates in the development and execution of research projects and public sector collaborations exploring emerging technologies and trends in public policy. Izzy is an experienced professional in policy and data analysis with an interest in delivering consulting and research services to clients.

EDUCATION:

Georgetown University, Washington, DC

M.P.S. summa cum laude in Urban and Regional Planning, August 2021

Concentrations: Policy, data analysis, spatial analysis, quantitative methods

Thesis: Smart City Planning: Using Machine Learning to Develop Local Household Eviction Prevention Strategies. Advised by Dr. Eric Dunford.

University of Nevada, Reno

B.A. cum laude in Political Science and Communication Studies, Fall 2016

PROFESSIONAL EXPERIENCE:

Georgetown University, Massive Data Institute, Washington, DC

Research Specialist, August 2021 - Present

- Conducts complex tabular and spatial data analysis in RStudio, utilizing fuzzy matching, machine learning, and various spatial analysis methods.
- Creates interactive and data-driven dashboard visualizations utilizing Esri and Tableau to inform data users on the utility and issues with various administrative data sources, primarily census data products.
- Manages dozens of grant deliverables related to data governance, administrative data linkage, population estimates methodology, and more.
- Consults local government officials on strategies related to population measurement modeling, data governance, and administrative data linkage for program evaluation and long-term planning.
- Translates and presents high-level research findings and policy recommendations to funders, stakeholders, and the public through compelling seminars, blogs, reports, infographics, and presentations.
- Coordinates coalition groups including the Census Products Alliance and the Eviction Data Coalition with the
 mission of engaging diverse and interdisciplinary communities around administrative data education and
 technical assistance.

Georgetown University, Massive Data Institute, Washington, DC

Project Manager, October 2019 - August 2021

- Served as an effective project and product manager across several projects, assisting Principal Investigators in completing grant proposals, developing budgets, and outlining work plans for deliverables.
- Reviewed applications, hired, onboarded, and supervised over one dozen research assistants for the unit and coached them on how to contribute to tasks that aligned with their interests, connecting them to growth opportunities relevant to their research interests.
- Coordinated program operations, performed project and product management tasks, and developed procedure standards and documentation in support of MDI's overall strategic plan.

• Monitored the staffing and financial components of research projects in a \$2.9 million project portfolio to meet contractual and reporting requirements by various public and private funding entities.

Georgetown University, Global Cities Initiative, Washington, DC

Graduate Fellow, January 2021 - June 2021

- Developed an ArcGIS Urban model of the Friendship Heights area to simulate development proposals for a studio course.
- Developed a workshop in collaboration with Esri's Solution Engineer for Smart City Solutions on utilizing ArcGIS Urban for students in the studio course.
- Performed a conditions assessment to identify the major opportunities for Georgetown to expand their support of spatial analysis and thinking.
- Authored a report on the obstacles and opportunities for expanding the use of GIS across the Georgetown campus based on conditions assessment and stakeholder engagement.

Georgetown Business Improvement District, Washington, DC

Data Science Intern, May 2020 - July 2020

- Analyzed location data and various demographic and business data from open data sources to assess
 Georgetown's retail and office market performance as well as visitor and local resident transportation
 behavior.
- Automated the collection and visualization of bikeshare utilization data which leveraged the Capital Bikeshare API endpoints and referenced the results into a Tableau dashboard.
- Designed, built, and launched Tableau dashboards to assess and visualize major financial trends in the Georgetown BID to contribute to economic development and COVID-19 recovery approaches.

Urban Institute, Office of Technology and Data Science, Washington, DC

Academic Intern, January 2020 - May 2020

- Conducted a field scan to synthesize case studies and scientific literature for a report on equity promises and Smart City technology programs in public administration.
- Wrote one dozen memos assessing various Smart City and equity initiatives around the country, comparing how public procurement and administration practices affected equity promises.
- Contributed to the development of a bias assessment tool by using R to spatially join points and polygons to census tracts, which automatically generates reports on the demographic bias of data sets.

Truckee Meadows Regional Planning Agency, Reno, NV

Intern, January 2019 - August 2019

- Contributed to the Truckee Meadows Regional Plan update's draft policies.
- Represented the agency at regional planning meetings, oversaw the clerking responsibilities for commission meetings, and facilitated public comment forums.

The Lockard Group, Carson City, NV

Legislative Assistant, February 2019 – June 2019

- Developed and carried out a legislative agenda by lobbying state lawmakers, analyzing legislation, suggesting amendments, providing testimony, tracking bills, and writing reports.
- Built a broad legislative coalition through strategic partnerships to advance the legislative priorities of clients, including hospital worker protections, eviction record sealing, affordable housing development streamlining, a

- low-income housing database, tenant protection laws, and legislation increasing state contributions to the Low-Income Housing Tax Credit fund.
- Coordinated the annual Grassroots Lobby Days for the Nevada Women's Lobby, with over 200 guests, panelists, and speakers from the Nevada State Legislature.

Truckee Meadows Regional Planning Agency, Reno, NV

Intern, January 2019 - June 2019

- Analyzed and prepared revisions for the Truckee Meadows Regional Plan update's draft policies to translate a regional vision into specific, actionable, and measurable policies related to population growth, regional form, public facilities and services, natural resources, and regional coordination.
- Administered and preserved the administrative record of Regional Planning Governing Board and Regional Planning Commission meetings, producing complete and accurate documentation in transcribed minute reports.

GRANTS:

Robert Wood Johnson Foundation, "Building Connections to Advance the Use of Place-Based Indicators", \$1.18M. January 2022 – January 2024.

Pew Charitable Trusts, "Civil Justice Data Commons", \$496k. November 2021 - March 2023.

New Venture Fund, "State Capacity Building for Census Challenges", \$200k. March 2021 - October 2021.

Tableau Foundation, "2020 Census Count Assessment Tool", \$296.4k. January 2021 – December 2021.

Sloan Foundation, "State Population Estimates", \$597.7k. August 2019 – July 2021.

Sloan Foundation, "Administrative Data Research Initiative", \$1.692 million. January 2019 – December 2020.

PUBLICATIONS:

- "Balancing Utility Versus Privacy in the 2020 Census: Sentiments from Data Users" Publication forthcoming.

 Izzy Youngs and Joseph Scariano. Massive Data Institute, McCourt School of Public Policy, Georgetown University. April 2022.
- A Crash Course on the Census Bureau's TopDown Algorithm. Izzy Youngs. Massive Data Institute, McCourt School of Public Policy, Georgetown University. March 2022.
- Who is Missing from Administrative Data? Izzy Youngs, Amy O'Hara, and Lahy Amman. Massive Data Institute, McCourt School of Public Policy, Georgetown University. August 2020.
- Using Administrative Data for Economic Stimulus. Izzy Youngs and Amy O'Hara. Massive Data Institute, McCourt School of Public Policy, Georgetown University. July 2020.

PRESENTATIONS:

Michigan Institute for Data Science (MIDAS) Data For Public Good symposium. Virtual

 $March\ 2022$

HONORS AND AWARDS:

Chair, 2021 Graduate Planning Society, Georgetown University Urban and Regional Planning Awardee, 2021 Community Builder Award, Georgetown University Urban and Regional Planning Awardee, 2020 Geospatial Prize, Georgetown University Urban and Regional Planning

TECHNICAL SKILLS:

- Spatial analysis and automation using ArcGIS Pro and R (sf framework)
- Data visualization and cartography with Tableau, Mapbox, ArcGIS Pro, QGIS, and R (ggplot3)
- Programming in web-based environments such as Google Cloud Platform, Colab, and Jupyter Notebook
- Data wrangling and analysis with R (tidyverse framework)
- Web design and documentation with RMarkdown, HTML/CSS, WordPress, and Google Sites
- Academic research organization and formatting using Zotero and LaTeX